<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Funded Projects | Matthew R. Siegfried</title>
    <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Funded Projects</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/img/rosetta-crevasse.jpg</url>
      <title>Funded Projects</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating NASA Cryosphere and ICESat-2 science with collaborative cloud computing</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/cryo_in_the_cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/cryo_in_the_cloud/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://science.nasa.gov/open-science/transform-to-open-science&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NASA Transform to Open Science &lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://icesat-2.gsfc.nasa.gov/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NASA ICESat-2 Project Science Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 1 October 2022 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 30 September 2024 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt; University of Berkeley, 2i2c, University of Washington, University of New Hampshire&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science is not composed of isolated groups of practitioners, but is rather an interconnected network of communities of practice, with members that fluidly move between them. Infrastructure for scientific research and collaboration should lean into this structure and find ways to leverage it to make science more productive and inclusive. NASA (along with many other scientific entities) has started to adopt practices consistent with this natural structure of contemporary science. Communities such as Project Jupyter and Pangeo have started to create a model for the inclusive, interconnected, and data-intensive practices of the future through cloud-based JupyterHub workflows. However, substantial barriers exist for individual users to make the transition from their local systems to the cloud to accomplish research goals: cloud cost opacity, deployment complexity, and a general lack of community awareness and knowledge, among others. We can overcome these barriers by building upon the existing cloud-workflow model and creating infrastructure that allows researchers to fluidly move their workflows wherever they can do their best work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have two projects, led by postdoctoral scholar 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://geophysics.mines.edu/project/tasha-snow/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Tasha Snow&lt;/a&gt; and visiting PhD student 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://eapsweb.mit.edu/people/jdmill&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Joanna Millstein&lt;/a&gt;, to establish a curated interactive computing platform and develop community expertise in using these platforms with the NASA ICESat-2 Science Team and the larger NASA Cryospheric Science Community during the NASA Year of Open Science in 2023. Specifically, we will (1) provide cloud and community expert-led training workshops at multiple community venues (including ICESat-2 Science Team meetings, the Future of Greenland ice Sheet Science (FOGSS) Workshop, the West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) Workshop, and the American Geophysical Unioin Fall Meeting), and (2) build new open-source tools that facilitate the growth of multi-community infrastructure. To accomplish these goals, we will partner with the International Interactive Computing Collaboration (2i2c) team, who will operate and develop the cloud-infrastructure - to manage and operate community-specific infrastructure, developing and improving the open source tools behind it, and guiding these communities in their use of these tools.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Teaching old data new tricks: Leveraging legacy field data to investigate ice-stream shut down and inspire a new generation of cryospheric scientists</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/career_whillans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/career_whillans/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2145407&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NSF CAREER Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 1 August 2022 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 13 July 2027&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Antarctic ice streams and outlet glaciers are the primary conduits of glacier ice from the interior of the continent to the ocean, where net ice loss contributes to global sea-level rise. Any process that speeds up or slows down the rate at which these ice streams move can appreciably impact the balance between ice gain and loss in Antarctica, with important implications for coastal communities worldwide. Processes that can lead to ice-stream acceleration are frequently studied, whereas ice-stream stagnation, which most recently occurred in Antarctica about 180 years ago, is studied less often. This project will leverage two decades of existing data from field experiments in Antarctica on a decelerating ice stream. The team will re-process these datasets from five different NSF-funded projects using modern geophysical methods to build long time-series of observations that provide insight into ice-sheet processes and test hypotheses about how stagnation occurs. In parallel, the team will leverage existing experiential field data to develop unique immersive learning modules to provide an accessible mechanism for the next generation of STEM students to experience Antarctic field work. Finally, this CAREER award will support a new pathway for a diverse cohort of researchers in the glaciology community by establishing and hosting annual regional Colorado Glaciology meetings that will connect community college educators and local glaciology researchers to exchange ideas, develop collaborations, and advertise opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over a quarter century of previous work has proposed that Whillans Ice Stream, West Antarctica, may stagnate by the mid-21st century, yet the processes that drive stagnation are still largely considered only in coarse, idealized terms. This project will leverage 13 years of continuous Global Positioning System data and 29 years of seismic data to interrogate ice-stream deceleration and stagnation processes. The multi-decadal datasets will indicate the evolution of stick-slip motion of the ice stream, long-term and spatially varying ice-thickening trends, and subglacial lake activity. These data will be used to explore how coupled ice-stream/subglacial-hydrology dynamics may lead to ultimate stagnation. In addition to the scientific investigations, the team will ensure the long-term archiving of unprocessed legacy field data to support the ability of future generations to apply novel techniques to past datasets. This project will include research experiences for students from the Colorado community college system and will develop three educational modules using low-cost immersive technologies to inspire and promote ice-sheet science to students from 6th grade to graduate school as well as the public.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying bias and uncertainty sources between laser and radar retrievals of surface topography over cryospheric targets</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/dsi/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/dsi/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/viewrepositorydocument/cmdocumentid=854093/solicitationId=%7B666D7B9E-7538-92FE-4BF6-63FFD313B47F%7D/viewSolicitationDocument=1/CRYO21%20Abstracts.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NASA Decadal Survey Incubation Program Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 15 June 2022 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 14 June 2025  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt; Washington University, St. Louis&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accurate quantification of the primary observables identified by the Surface Topography and Vegetation (STV) working group bare surface land topography, ice topography, vegetation structure, shallow water bathymetry, and snow depth requires geodetic measurements with sub-meter vertical resolution and sub-weekly temporal repeat-sampling. A multi-sensor fusion approach combining lidar, radar, and stereophotogrammetry from both orbital and suborbital platforms will likely be necessary to achieve these resolution requirements. However, a thorough investigation of the biases and uncertainties inherent to each of these geodetic measurements, as well as how these biases and uncertainties might compound in a multi-sensor fusion approach, is needed before any such multi-sensor framework can be developed and optimized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project led by former Mines Glaciology Laboratory postdoctoral scholar 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://eps.wustl.edu/people/roger-michaelides&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Roger Michaelides&lt;/a&gt;, we  investigate the sources of measurement bias and uncertainty in orbital laser altimetry, radar altimetry, and interferometric synthetic aperture radar (InSAR) measurements over ice sheet surfaces and periglacial land surfaces. These two surface types are subject to the time- and space-varying surface dielectric properties of snow, ice, and surface water, and subjected to seasonal and interannual geomorphic processes that can reshape surface topography (such as sub- or supra-glacial lake drainage at ice sheet boundaries and permafrost thaw and thermokarst initiation in periglacial regions), all of which complicate the error inherent in and interpretation of surface height measurements. We have three cross-cutting objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Characterize and reduce sources of uncertainty and biases in laser altimetry, radar altimetry, and InSAR measurements over ice sheet surfaces and periglacial land surfaces.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Quantify the effect of these uncertainties on vertical and rate of change accuracies for both cryospheric and solid-earth/hydrologic targets.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop and test novel multi-sensor data fusion methods and algorithms that leverage complementary geodetic measurements for improved topographic products and temporal-repeat measurements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seeds of Change: Investigating the Impact of Antarctic Basal Channel and Persistent Polynya Co-Evolution on Ice Shelf Stability</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/cryo_polynyas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/cryo_polynyas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/viewrepositorydocument/cmdocumentid=854093/solicitationId=%7B666D7B9E-7538-92FE-4BF6-63FFD313B47F%7D/viewSolicitationDocument=1/CRYO21%20Abstracts.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NASA Cryospheric Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 1 February 2022 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 31 January 2025  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt; University of Colorado Boulder, University of Manitoba, University of St Andrews, University of Berkeley&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice shelves and their tributary glaciers that drain Antarctica account for almost the entirety of net mass loss from the Antarctic Ice Sheet, the source of the greatest uncertainty in 21st-century sea-level rise projections. Nearly half of the glacier ice that reaches the ocean to form floating ice shelves is lost to basal melting by the ocean. This melting varies substantially in time and space as a result of complex climate, ocean, and ice interactions, making projections of future ice loss difficult. In particular, enhanced localized basal melt rates can incise ice-shelf basal channels that may structurally weaken ice shelves. Many of these channels convey water sourced from the upstream locations where the channels form to the edge of the ice shelf. This outflow often includes residually warm ocean water with enough heat to maintain local sea icefree ocean conditions seasonally or year-round for small areas near the ice front, known as persistent polynyas. The water in these polynyas represents a mixture between the ocean water mass that initiated basal melt and the melt content entrained as the water exits the ice shelf cavity. Variability in these features over time, as a result of climate and  oceanographic changes, provides insight into ice-shelf evolution (e.g., strain and melt rates) and the processes that can weaken ice shelves. However, mapping of basal channels and their impact on ice-shelf evolution are limited. Further, direct in situ outflow measurements are sparse and little work has explored the use of remote sensing for this task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project led by postdoctoral scholar 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://geophysics.mines.edu/project/tasha-snow/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr. Tasha Snow&lt;/a&gt;, we will use optical and thermal infrared imagery from the Landsat 7 through 9, Aqua and Terra, Sentinel-2, and Sentinel-3A/B instrumentation in a multi-sensor and multi-modal data fusion investigation that will assess the characteristics variability of the persistent polynya ice-ocean features in Antarctica. Data from field observations and ICESat-2 laser altimetry will be examined using modern machine learning approaches and cloud-based, open-sourced workflows. The proposed work is organized around three specific goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automate persistent polynya detection and characterization for community use;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimize Landsat, MODIS, and Sentinel-3 SST retrievals to build year-round upper ocean temperature records for multiple Antarctic basal channel outflows; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assess ice shelf and water outflow co-evolution using a data fusion framework for deriving ice shelf and ocean parameters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Investigating four decades of Ross Ice Shelf subsurface change with historical and modern radar sounding data</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/spri_rosetta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 15 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/spri_rosetta/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=2049302&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NSF Antarctic Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 15 August 2021 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 14 August 2024  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt; Georgia Tech (lead), Stanford University&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ice shelves play a critical role in restricting the seaward flow of grounded glacier ice by providing buttressing at their bases and sides. Processes that affect the long-term stability of ice shelves can therefore influence the future contribution of the Antarctic Ice Sheet to global sea-level rise. The Ross Ice Shelf is the largest ice shelf on Earth, and it buttresses massive areas of West and East Antarctica. Previous studies of modern ice velocity indicated that the Ross Ice Shelf’s mass loss is roughly balanced by its mass gain. However, more recent work that extends further back in time reveals the ice shelf is likely not in steady state, with possible long-term thinning since the late 1990s. Consequently, to accurately interpret modern-day ice-shelf changes, long-term observations are critical to evaluate how these recent variations fit into the historical context of ice-shelf variability. This project will examine more than four decades of historical and modern airborne radar sounding observations of the Ross Ice Shelf (spanning 1971 to 2017) to investigate ice-shelf changes on decadal timescales. The team will process, calibrate, and analyze radar data collected during 1971-79 field campaigns and compare them against modern observations collected between 2011-17. They will estimate basal melt rates by examining changes in ice-shelf thickness, and will determine other important metrics for melt, including ice-shelf roughness, englacial temperature, and marine-ice formation. The project will support the education of a Ph.D. student at each of the three participating institutions. In addition, the project will support the training of undergraduate and high-school researchers in radioglaciology and Antarctic sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project will test the hypothesis that, over decadal timescales, the basal melt rates beneath the Ross Ice Shelf have been low, particularly under shallow ice drafts, leading to overall thickening and increased buttressing potential. The team aims to provide a direct estimate of basal melt rates based on changes in ice-shelf thickness that occurred between 1971 and 2017. This project will extend similar work completed at Thwaites Glacier and improve the calibration methods on the vertical scaling for fast-time and depth conversion. The work will also leverage the dense modern surveys to improve the geolocation of radar film collected on earlier field campaigns to produce a more precise comparison of local shelf thickness with the modern data. In addition, the team will conduct englacial attenuation analysis to calculate englacial temperature to infer the trends in local basal melting. They will also examine the radiometric and scatterometric character of bed echoes at the ice-ocean boundary to characterize changes in ice-shelf basal roughness, marine-ice formation related to local basal freezing, and structural damage from fracture processes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging ICESat-2 altimetry for Antarctic subglacial lake identification, evolution, and basal properties</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/icesat2_science-team/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/icesat2_science-team/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/viewrepositorydocument/cmdocumentid=800798/solicitationId=%7B26E97B17-21F2-26AE-D907-0BF9B458A05F%7D/viewSolicitationDocument=1/GNSS19%20selections_updated.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NASA Studies with ICESat-2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 1 May 2021 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 30 April 2024  &lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Results from the Ice, Cloud, and land Elevation Satellite (ICESat), as well as aereogeophysical and ground-based surveys, revealed that the fast flowing portions of the Antarctic ice sheet are underlain by complex, dynamic hydrological systems. These timeevolving systems have the ability to control regional ice velocity, change grounding-line stability, and discharge freshwater and micronutrients to the sub-ice-shelf coastal environment. Hidden beneath 10s to 1000s of meters of ice, processes related to these enigmatic hydrological systems of interconnected lakes and streams are poorly understood, largely due to the limited temporal window of our active subglacial lake icesurface observational record from which we infer systematic subglacial hydrological dynamics, our simplified mechanical models of how subglacial lakes deform the overlying ice, and the lack of instrumentation to record downstream impacts. We propose to develop methods for retrieving dynamic ice surface-height changes from ICESat-2 laser altimetry that leverage the high spatial resolution and vertical precision of ICESat-2 data to better quantify Antarctic active subglacial lake location, magnitude, and stability from the coast to 88°S. Our work will couple our high precision retrieval of surfaceheight change to a newly developed, quantitative mechanical model to investigate and evaluate the relationship between surface-height change and properties of the subglacial environment, including subglacial water mass balance, fast versus slow drainage behaviors, and lakeshore migration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our proposed work will consist of two interrelated objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Analyze ICESat-2 laser altimetry land-ice surface heights (the ATL06 data product), combined with ICESat and Operation IceBridge laser altimetry and CryoSat-2 radar altimetry, to extend and refine our multidecadal time series of dynamic hydrology systems beneath Antarctica, including generating high resolution, time-evolving maps of lake locations; and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leverage the increased spatial resolution of ICESat-2 compared to previous altimeters to identify previously undetected areas of dynamic height change on the grounded ice sheet and apply novel statistical methods to quantify our confidence in the driver of these height anomalies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Constraining West Antarctic snow accumulation and firn densification processes with GNSS reflectometry</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/gnss_snowfall/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/gnss_snowfall/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/viewrepositorydocument/cmdocumentid=800798/solicitationId=%7B26E97B17-21F2-26AE-D907-0BF9B458A05F%7D/viewSolicitationDocument=1/GNSS19%20selections_updated.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NASA GNSS Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 1 September 2020 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 31 August 2023  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt; NASA Goddard Space Flight Center&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Projections of ice sheet mass balance and consequent sea-level rise are complicated by large uncertainties in modeling surface mass balance processes, such as snow accumulation, snow redistribution, melt, and firn compaction. In situ observations for constraining model physics and validating coupled atmosphere-ice sheet models are sparse, especially in Antarctica where surface mass balance amounts to approximately 2600 Gt of mass input per year. With more than 7 mm/yr of sea-level equivalent accumulating as snow across Antarctica, surface mass balance variability has the potential to substantially impact the rate of sea-level rise, currently estimated to be ~3 mm/yr. We propose to use an existing array of 118 long-term global navigation satellite system (GNSS) instruments from the West Antarctic Ice Sheet and Ross Ice Shelf to observe net snow accumulation and firn compaction across highly variable surface mass balance regimes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Classical GNSS processing for glaciological applications uses direct-signal positioning techniques to resolve three dimensional ice-sheet motion. Instead, we will use the reflected GNSS signal as a signal of opportunity to generate time series of the height of each GNSS antenna above the snow surface using interferometric reflectometry (GNSS-IR). The GNSS stations we will use were deployed for variable time periods, ranging from two weeks to over ten years, providing both short- and long-term insight into snow accumulation, melt, and firn compaction. Our project will consist of four interrelated objectives: (1) Optimization of GNSS-IR processing for higher-resolution surface evolution both in time and in space for understanding the scientific questions this method can answer; (2) Use GNSS-IR time series to validate radar-sounding- and satellite altimetry-derived snow accumulation and firn compaction rates across variable surface mass balance regimes; (3) Improve the representation of surface processes in firn densification models and optimize model calibration using GNSS-IR results; and (4) Compare long-term trends between GNSS-IR observations and firn densification models to quantify and partition uncertainty to its sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our work will integrate GNSS-IR observations with ground-based terrestrial laser scanning, NASA’s Operation IceBridge radar sounding surveying, European Space Agency’s radar altimetry missions (ERS-1/-2, Envisat, CryoSat-2), and NASA’s ICESat-2 laser altimetry mission. We will interpret these observations in the context of state-ofthe-art climate models developed at NASA Goddard Space Flight Center (MERRA-2, NASA-GSFC firn model) in order to validate and improve the capabilities of these models. Our effort to observe surface mass balance processes with GNSS-IR will be particularly important for ground validation of ICESat-2 altimetry, for reducing uncertainty in the conversion of ICESat-2-observed ice-volume change to ice-mass change, and for pushing forward our ability to combine radar and laser satellite altimetry results. Finally, the proposed work will help drive the development of surface-process models in Antarctica that effectively capture spatial scales driven by topographic variability and time scales of single weather events, one of the goals deemed “Most Important” by the 2017 NASA Decadal Survey (H-1c), as well as contribute many other climate variability questions (e.g., C-1a, C-1c, C-8b) laid out by this report.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Observationally Constrained Simulations of the Evolution of Polar Snow Using a Multi-Sensor Approach</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/ids/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/ids/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/viewrepositorydocument/cmdocumentid=765904/solicitationId=%7B8713AEB5-29AA-57DF-BCDE-518CA1F973FF%7D/viewSolicitationDocument=1/IDS19%20Abstracts.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NASA Interdisciplinary Research in Earth Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 1 September, 2020 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 31 August 2023&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt; NASA Goddard Space Flight Center (lead), University of Oregon, University of Washington, University of Colorado Boulder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The life cycle of snow is one of the most critical unknowns of the polar climate system. We seek to to fill this urgent gap in our understanding of Earth’s atmosphere-ice-ocean interactions by producing observationally constrained models of all stages of the life cycle of snow over ice sheets. Specifically, we employ observations of snowfall and rainfall rates (CloudSat), surface height change (ICESat, ICESat-2, GNSS reflectometry, AWS), snow thickness (Operation IceBridge snow radar), blowing snow fluxes (ICESat, ICESat-2), albedo and timing of bare ice exposure (MODIS), mass change (GRACE, GRACE-FO), and microwave brightness temperatures (SSM/I, SSM/IS, AMSR-E, AMSR2). Individually, these observations provide mediocre constraints on snow evolution since they target a specific stage of the life cycle; in conjunction, they provide independent controls on the entire system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pingo SubTerranean Aquifer Reconnaissance and Reconstruction (Pingo STARR)</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/pingostarr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/pingostarr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/viewrepositorydocument/cmdocumentid=743002/solicitationId=%7B602BD10E-6083-2C21-36B9-DE0C17B1774C%7D/viewSolicitationDocument=1/PSTAR19%20Abstracts.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NASA Planetary Science and Technology from Analog Research&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 1 July, 2020 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 30 June 2024&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt; University of Alaska Anchorage, Cornell University (lead), Planetary Science Institute&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mars, Ceres, and the Earth have abundant reserves of ground ice. On Earth, ice-cored mounds known as pingos are important indicators of extant and extinct near-surface groundwater systems, hydrologic properties, and local climate. Spacecraft observations of Mars and Ceres have revealed a variety of deca- to kilometer scale hills with morphological similarities to terrestrial pingos in ice-rich environments. Pingo STARR will advance human and lander scale geophysical techniques specifically tailored to detect, characterize, and investigate the cryohydrology and genesis of possible pingo-like features on Earth, Mars, and Ceres. This systems-level field campaign will be the most comprehensive to date for any terrestrial pingos, and the first dedicated analysis of pingos from a planetary science perspective. Our science and technology objectives will provide valuable insight into detecting and characterizing ground-ice and -water systems on Mars and Ceres.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The West Antarctic Ice Sheet (WAIS) Workshop</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/wais_workshop/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/wais_workshop/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; NASA Cryospheric Science and NSF Antarctic Science&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 1 August 2019 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 31 July 2023  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt; University of Washington, University of Minnesota, University of Florida, University of Virginia, NASA Goddard Space Flight Center&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.waisworkshop.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;WAIS Workshop&lt;/a&gt; has been held annually for the past 25 years, providing a venue for transdisciplinary scientific exchange on the state and behavior of the West Antarctic Ice Sheet, processes that influence its changing behavior, and projections of its future mass balance and sea-level contribution. These awards from NASA and NSF fund us to host the 2019, 2020, 2021, and 2022 WAIS Workshops.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the error distribution of Operation IceBridge swath altimetry to generate robust, long-duration time series of height changes over dyanmic features in Antarctica</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/icebridge/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/icebridge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nspires.nasaprs.com/external/viewrepositorydocument/cmdocumentid=555585/solicitationId=%7BD244F3AA-37A1-4199-BDB4-F62FA4C34EBD%7D/viewSolicitationDocument=1/ICEBRIDGE16%20SELECTIONS_2.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NASA Operation IceBridge Science Team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 1 April 2019 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 31 March 2021  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt; Scripps Institution of Oceanography (lead)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As part of the Operation IceBridge Science Team, we worked to better quantify cm-scale errors in lidar data in order to generate robust, long-duration time series of dynamic surface features of the Antarctic ice sheet.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SALSA EM: Mapping Subglacial Groundwater in Antarctica</title>
      <link>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/salsa_em/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://mrsiegfried.github.io/projects/salsa_em/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Funding Program:&lt;/strong&gt; 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://nsf.gov/awardsearch/showAward?AWD_ID=1643917&amp;amp;HistoricalAwards=false&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NSF Antarctic Science&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Start Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 1 December 2017 &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;End Date:&lt;/strong&gt; 30 November 2022  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Collaborating Institutions:&lt;/strong&gt; Scripps Institution of Oceanography (lead), Columbia University&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Antarctic ice sheet is underlain by a dynamic water system that lubricates the flow of ice streams and outlet glaciers, provides a habitat for a diverse microbial ecosystem, and delivers freshwater and nutrients to the Southern Ocean. However, imaging this subglacial environment is difficult: Antarctica is a vast continent with ice up to four kilometers (2.5 miles) thick. To detect water at the ice-bed interface and in deeper groundwater reservoirs, this project will adapt a technique called electromagnetic sounding that is well-established on land and in the ocean for imaging fluids beneath the surface. Groundwater is estimated to be a significant part of the subglacial water budget in Antarctica, yet previous observational approaches have been unable to characterize its volume and distribution. This project will thus yield critical information about how ice-rock-water-ocean systems interact and inform our understanding of ice-sheet processes, global nutrient cycles, and freshwater flux to the ocean. The project will provide cross-disciplinary training for a graduate student and postdoctoral scientist, and develop an educational outreach program through the Birch Aquarium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Standard geophysical surveying techniques used in glaciology to image subglacial water (radio-echo sounding and active-source seismology) are not directly sensitive to water content. In contrast, ground-based electromagnetic (EM) methods are sensitive to water content through its impact on bulk conductivity. Although EM methods are well-established for high-precision mapping of hydrology in other geological environments, their application on ice sheets is in its infancy. The proposed work will adapt both passive- and active-source EM techniques to glaciological questions to quantify the three-dimensional structure of subglacial water beneath an ice stream and in a grounding zone. The project will perform a suite of synthetic inversion studies to determine the range of applications of EM techniques in glaciology and execute a field experiment on the Whillans Ice Plain to investigate two hypotheses about the subglacial water system based on previous observational and modeling results: (1) Subglacial Lake Whillans is underlain by a deep, saline groundwater reservoir; and (2) there is an estuary-like zone of mixing between fresh subglacial water and seawater near, and possibly landward, of the grounding line.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
